<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marta Mendes da Rocha | Lucas Gelape</title>
    <link>/en/authors/marta-mendes-da-rocha/</link>
      <atom:link href="/en/authors/marta-mendes-da-rocha/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Marta Mendes da Rocha</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en</language><copyright>© 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu1d16897e3fa93fcb083438e47d0c5cbc_11292_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Marta Mendes da Rocha</title>
      <link>/en/authors/marta-mendes-da-rocha/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Political affairs&#34;: brokerage relationships between state representatives and local politicians in Brazil</title>
      <link>/en/publication/political_affairs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/publication/political_affairs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rocha, Marta Mendes and Lucas Gelape. 2023. &amp;ldquo;Political affairs&amp;rdquo;: brokerage relationships between state representatives and local politicians in Brazil. &lt;strong&gt;SciELO Preprints&lt;/strong&gt;. (Trabalho original disponibilizado em 2022).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Brazil, politicians at different levels cooperate to achieve electoral and governing goals. Recently, these relationships have come to be analyzed through theories of brokers developed in comparative politics. This article investigates the micro-foundations of alliances between state representatives and local politicians and asks to what extent those theories are adequate to analyze these relationships in Brazil. Our analysis combines data from surveys with state representatives and interviews with advisors and focuses on how alliances are built, maintained, and broken. We show that mayors and city councilors are important brokers for state representatives. However, the fact that legislators and local brokers do not hold static positions and play dual roles underscores the limits of principal-agent theories to describe and analyze these relationships. Based on our conclusions, we suggest pathways to advance our understanding of the dynamics of interest intermediation and the multilevel connections between political actors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure: Two most important supports for the election of state legislators&lt;/strong&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./brokers_estaduais.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Source: prepared by the authors based on data from CEL-UFMG.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Note: each respondent is counted twice, because a legislator gives an answer for both the most important support and the second most important.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
