<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lucas Gelape</title>
    <link>/en/authors/admin/</link>
      <atom:link href="/en/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Lucas Gelape</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en</language><copyright>© 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/en/authors/admin/avatar_huf91b8b90f95707e884164326a1f0aa54_1300289_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Lucas Gelape</title>
      <link>/en/authors/admin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Candidacies and Mandates in Brazil: Challenges and Pitfalls of a Gambiarra</title>
      <link>/en/publication/mandatos_coletivos_gambiarra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/publication/mandatos_coletivos_gambiarra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mendonça, Ricardo Fabrino, Lucas Gelape and Carlos Estevão C. Cruz. 2023. Collective Candidacies and Mandates in Brazil: Challenges and Pitfalls of a Gambiarra. In: Bua, Adrian; Bussu, Sonia (org.). &lt;strong&gt;Reclaiming Participatory Governance: social movements and the reinvention of democratic innovation&lt;/strong&gt;. New York: Routledge, p. 154-159.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, we examine the democratic innovation of collective candidacies and mandates in Brazil. These candidacies can be defined as a group formed within a party list to run together for a single seat in parliament. These groups usually adopt participatory practices on their campaigns and, when elected, in their legislative activities. Such innovation arose from a crisis of legitimacy of representative institutions in the country, which deepened over the last decade. We read this phenomenon through the idea of gambiarra (which can be translated as a kludge, workaround or stopgap). This gambiarra reinvents electoral politics through improvisation, amid institutional constraints, currently happening in a legal limbo of uncertainty and open possibilities. By making sense of this phenomenon as a gambiarra, we stress its precarious yet creative status. The chapter presents the capacity of collective candidacies and mandates to renovate institutional politics, while pointing out some limitations and risks derived from these practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure: Percentage of city council candidacies per race/ethnicity and age in the Brazilian 2020 elections.&lt;/strong&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./collective_candidacies.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Source: created by the authors from &lt;a href=&#34;https://npms.paginas.ufsc.br/files/2021/01/MandatosColetivos_RelatorioPesquisa_2021JAN08.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Secchi e Leal&amp;rsquo;s (2020) data.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Political affairs&#34;: brokerage relationships between state representatives and local politicians in Brazil</title>
      <link>/en/publication/political_affairs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/publication/political_affairs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rocha, Marta Mendes and Lucas Gelape. 2023. &amp;ldquo;Political affairs&amp;rdquo;: brokerage relationships between state representatives and local politicians in Brazil. &lt;strong&gt;SciELO Preprints&lt;/strong&gt;. (Trabalho original disponibilizado em 2022).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Brazil, politicians at different levels cooperate to achieve electoral and governing goals. Recently, these relationships have come to be analyzed through theories of brokers developed in comparative politics. This article investigates the micro-foundations of alliances between state representatives and local politicians and asks to what extent those theories are adequate to analyze these relationships in Brazil. Our analysis combines data from surveys with state representatives and interviews with advisors and focuses on how alliances are built, maintained, and broken. We show that mayors and city councilors are important brokers for state representatives. However, the fact that legislators and local brokers do not hold static positions and play dual roles underscores the limits of principal-agent theories to describe and analyze these relationships. Based on our conclusions, we suggest pathways to advance our understanding of the dynamics of interest intermediation and the multilevel connections between political actors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure: Two most important supports for the election of state legislators&lt;/strong&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./brokers_estaduais.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Source: prepared by the authors based on data from CEL-UFMG.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Note: each respondent is counted twice, because a legislator gives an answer for both the most important support and the second most important.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Party restriction on career decisions of Brazilian politicians: evidence from Brazilian city councilors</title>
      <link>/en/publication/restricao_partidaria/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/publication/restricao_partidaria/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gelape, Lucas; Silva, Glauco Peres da. 2022. Party restriction on career decisions of Brazilian politicians: evidence from Brazilian city councilors. &lt;strong&gt;Revista de Sociologia e Política&lt;/strong&gt;, v. 30, e014. (In Portuguese)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much does intra-party competition affect the career decisions of Brazilian politicians? We know that careers result from the interaction between individual wills, on the one hand, and political opportunity structure, on the other. The party instances are central elements in this structure and shape the composition of slates of candidates in an election, since they are the initial place of political dispute. Therefore, they should affect the career choices of Brazilian city councilors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Material and Methods:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We descriptively analyzed a survey applied to 422 city councilors from Minas Gerais in 2015. Based on this data, we compared the career choices declared by the councilmen with the candidacy record of these politicians in 2016 to verify the convergence between these two facts. Then, using data from all Brazilians councilors elected in 2012, we constructed a matched sample and estimated multivariate regression models to investigate the causal effect of intra-party competition on the probability of a city councilor running for mayor. Given the difficulty of observing intra-party competition, we created a proxy to identify competitive candidates according to characteristics prior to candidate registration in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survey reveals that the vast majority of city councilors who intended to run for mayor in 2016 did not run. Multivariate regression models show causal evidence that city councilors who faced intra-party competition were less likely to run for the municipal chief executive. We found no variation in this effect among the ten parties with the highest number of elected candidates, as well as among different electorate sizes, except for those with more than 1 million voters (in which the effect was null).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discussion:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intra-party competition proved to be an active and important constraint on the decisions of the individuals evaluated. Career choices are directly influenced by party dynamics even in local politics, exactly where the literature points to weaker ties between politicians and political parties. Therefore, it is necessary to extend this analysis to other offices and other types of representatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure: Office that the councilor declared the intention to run (2015) x Office that he effectively ran for&lt;/strong&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./intrapartidaria_sp.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Source: created by the authors from TSE&amp;rsquo;s and data from the survey &amp;ldquo;Political representation at the local level in Brazil&amp;rdquo; (Nepol/PPGCSO/UFJF, 2015). Note: the colors indicate the percentage of politicians that make a career decision, considering the office they declared an intention to run for.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In spite of all, local political careers: alternative patterns, incumbency advantage and political parties on city councilors trajectories</title>
      <link>/en/publication/tese/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/publication/tese/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gelape, Lucas. &lt;strong&gt;In spite of all, local political careers: alternative patterns, incumbency advantage and political parties on city councilors trajectories&lt;/strong&gt;. PhD Dissertation – University of São Paulo, São Paulo, 2022.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dissertation has two main goals. First, it tries to identify the pattern of political careers in Brazil, from the city councilor&amp;rsquo;s office. The theory has shown different career patterns in multi-level political systems, pointing out that the Brazilian case is closer to the &amp;ldquo;integrated&amp;rdquo; type. This finding, however, is a product of analysis based on federal deputies, while the comparative politics literature has shown the possibility of regional careers if the focus is shifted from the national lower houses. We propose to study careers that include a term as a city councilor in Brazil and conduct an investigation based on all the councilors elected between 2000 and 2020. Their trajectories show that almost all of them (more than 99%) never win a state-level electoral office and only circulate in local offices. This result, however, is conditioned on the city&amp;rsquo;s electorate, since in cities with more than 500,000 voters, councilors can win those state-level seats, in careers that &amp;ldquo;integrate&amp;rdquo; state and/or national offices. Thus, when looking from the city councilor office, there are alternative/equivalent career paths in the country, with two distinct possibilities, conditioned on the city&amp;rsquo;s electorate size. Our second goal is to investigate the role of the political opportunities structure on career decisions, by analyzing how two factors &amp;ndash; the incumbency and political parties &amp;ndash; can affect them. To study the first factor, we use a regression discontinuity design to study close elections and assess the incumbency advantage of city councilors elected between 2000 and 2016. We find that barely winners have a small electoral disadvantage measured by their unconditional reelection probability. Moreover, we find that incumbency has a positive effect on their decision to rerun, and a strong negative effect on their chances of winning if they decide to rerun (conditional probability). These results are close to those found for Brazilian mayors and diverge from those found for deputies. Finally, to assess the relevance of political parties, we test if the existence of co-partisans who would be competitive candidates for mayor affect the probability that a city councilor elected in 2012 would run for mayor in 2016. We first use a survey conducted with city councilors from the state of Minas Gerais and find that while a substantial number of them report in 2015 a wish to run for mayor, very few do run for it in 2016. Our identification strategy is based on a directed acyclic graph (DAG) to find the variables we should control for, a nearest neighbor matching on observations from all city councilors elected in 2012, and multivariate regressions to estimate the average treatment effect on the treated (ATT). We find evidence, robust to several specifications, that the treatment has a negative effect on the probability that city councilors who face competitive co-partisans end up running for mayor. Therefore, even in cities, where the bond between politicians and parties is arguably weaker, we find evidence that parties are an important factor in the electoral arena and have an effect on individuals&amp;rsquo; careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./tese.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The construction of political-territorial ties: evidence from of São Paulo</title>
      <link>/en/publication/indicacoes_sp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/publication/indicacoes_sp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hoyler, Telma; Gelape, Lucas; Silotto, Graziele. 2021. The construction of political-territorial ties: evidence from of São Paulo. &lt;strong&gt;Opinião Pública&lt;/strong&gt;, Campinas, v. 27, n. 2, p. 549–584. (In Portuguese)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current interpretations on the inner workings of Brazilian city councils are rooted in the scholarly debate of national politics. In the latter, the presence of legislation proposals with territorial goals and concentrated electoral voting patterns are the main evidence of distributivism/clientelism. We argue, however, that such characteristics of legislative and electoral politics at the national level are ill-suited proxies for analysis of the local level, failing to capture nuances of political mobilization in cities. Instead, by means of a mixed-methods analysis of an instrument called representatives’ requests – in-depth interviews, participant observation, and local spatial autocorrelation hypothesis tests – we argue that city councilors&amp;rsquo; geographically targeted actions take place through a capillary and rooted structure of brokers that feeds back and creates ties throughout local mandates and voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure: Lisa (Local Moran) from the number of representative&amp;rsquo;s requests by district &amp;ndash; councilors Dalton Silvano (13ª legislature) e Gilson Barreto (11ª legislature)&lt;/strong&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./indicacoes_op.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Source: created by the authors using data from São Paulo&amp;rsquo;s City Council and IBGE.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highlights</title>
      <link>/en/blog/destaques/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/destaques/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These are some of my work&amp;rsquo;s highlights. They are a combination of articles, data analysis, presentations, and tools that I produced over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/vantagens_reeleicao/&#34;&gt;The advantages of reelection&lt;/a&gt; (in Portuguese): op-ed published on &lt;em&gt;Folha de S. Paulo&lt;/em&gt;, in reply to former president Fernando Henrique Cardoso&amp;rsquo;s article against reelection;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/science_pulse/&#34;&gt;Science Pulse&lt;/a&gt;: app web development in &lt;code&gt;Shiny&lt;/code&gt; from this scientific community social listening tool;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/bolsonaro_aprovacao/&#34;&gt;Unlike other world leaders, Bolsonaro&amp;rsquo;s evaluation does not change during the pandemic&lt;/a&gt; (in Portuguese): analysis published on Núcleo Jornalismo, which was mentioned by other news outlets, such as &lt;em&gt;Jornal Nacional&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Folha de S. Paulo&lt;/em&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/materias_g1/&#34;&gt;News stories published on G1&lt;/a&gt; (in Portuguese): I point out 3 stories that brought new angles to stories that were covered by other news outlets. &lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/noticia/2018/07/29/em-23-das-cidades-do-pais-partidos-nao-declaram-despesas-de-2017.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;In 2/3 of the cities, parties do not report their 2017 expenses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; shows how parties organize across the country, trying to understand why they might not declare those expenses. &lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/08/numero-de-policiais-e-militares-no-legislativo-e-quatro-vezes-maior-do-que-o-de-2014.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The number of policemen and military elected for Legislative seats is four times higher than in 2014&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Gabriela Caesar and Ana Carolina Moreno) showed, on the night of the first round of the 2018 elections, that this number signaled the strength from the rightists&amp;rsquo; politicians coming from the polls. &lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/11/07/resultados-da-votacao-por-urna-mostram-dobradinhas-na-maioria-dos-estados-no-2o-turno.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results by electoral precint shows partnerships (&amp;ldquo;dobradinhas&amp;rdquo;) in the 2nd round of most states&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; uses very disaggregated data to better understand the second-round results from 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/geografia_eleicoes/&#34;&gt;Geocast&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;live&lt;/em&gt; where I discuss the research on Electoral Geography and how R can help on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science Pulse</title>
      <link>/en/blog/science_pulse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/science_pulse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m responsible for developing the main infrastructure and the curation algorithms for Science Pulse&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://sciencepulse.org/app/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;web app&lt;/a&gt;, which was written in &lt;code&gt;Shiny&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science Pulse is a social listening platform, which monitors and curates content from scientists, professors, experts, and research institutions on social media (currently on Twitter and Facebook).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app is &lt;em&gt;open-source&lt;/em&gt; and its&amp;rsquo; source code can be found at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/voltdatalab/science-pulse-public&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;its&amp;rsquo; GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is developed by Volt Data Lab, supported by the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ) and Agência Bori.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using data collected on Science Pulse, I also produced these news stories for Núcleo Jornalismo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/redes/2021-03-11-ciencia-dispara-twitter-divulgadores&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the midst of chaos, Brazilian science flourishes on  Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Alexandre Orrico), 11 mar. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/reportagem/2021-03-25-butantan-comunicao-digital&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;From snakes to funk: the shift on Instituto Butantan&amp;rsquo;s communication&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Laís Martins), 25 mar. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/curtas/2021-04-06-vazamento-facebook-dados-repercussao-twitter&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Experts mobilizing on social media in favor of lockdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 06 apr. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Núcleo Jornalismo - Politics</title>
      <link>/en/blog/nucleo_politica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/nucleo_politica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Núcleo Jornalismo&lt;/a&gt;, I contribute with data analysis and, occasionally, writing the stories. The news stories on politics (all in Portuguese) that I participated in are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/reportagem/2021-04-08-tabata-amaral-esquerda-ataques&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leftist social media hate Tabata Amaral. Why?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Sérgio Spagnuolo and Laís Martins), 08 apr. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/governo/2020-11-28-vereadores-jovens-brasil-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Share of young city councilors keep falling in Brazil&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 28 nov. 2020;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/media/2020-11-10-vereadores-reeleicao-desertos-noticia&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;In news deserts, city councilors run more for reelection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 10 nov. 2020;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/pesquisas/2020-04-01-popularidade-bolsonaro-lideres-coronavirus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unlike other world leaders, Bolsonaro&amp;rsquo;s evaluation does not change during the pandemic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 01 apr. 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Núcleo Jornalismo - Social Media</title>
      <link>/en/blog/nucleo_redes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/nucleo_redes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Núcleo Jornalismo&lt;/a&gt;, I contribute with data analysis and, occasionally, writing the stories. Recently, the website&amp;rsquo;s focus is the impact of social media on society. The news stories on social (all in Portuguese) that I participated in are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/especiais/2021-04-15-influencers-armas-instagram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guns are used for digital influence on Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Laís Martins), 15 apr. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/reportagem/2021-04-08-tabata-amaral-esquerda-ataques&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leftist social media hate Tabata Amaral. Why?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Sérgio Spagnuolo and Laís Martins), 08 apr. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/curtas/2021-04-06-vazamento-facebook-dados-repercussao-twitter&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Experts mobilizing on social media in favor of lockdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 06 apr. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/reportagem/2021-04-01-facebook-comercio-armas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Facebook is still used to buy and sell guns in Brazil&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 01 apr. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/reportagem/2021-03-25-butantan-comunicao-digital&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;From snakes to funk: the shift on Instituto Butantan&amp;rsquo;s communication&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Laís Martins), 25 mar. 2021;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/redes/2021-03-11-ciencia-dispara-twitter-divulgadores&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the midst of chaos, Brazilian science flourishes on  Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with Alexandre Orrico), 11 mar. 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects - Volt Data Lab</title>
      <link>/en/blog/voltdatalab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/voltdatalab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a data analyst at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.voltdata.info/en-lg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Volt Data Lab&lt;/a&gt;, I participate in some projects that involved data collection, analysis, and visualization, from many different sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/science_pulse/&#34;&gt;Science Pulse&lt;/a&gt;: an online tool to connect journalists to the scientific conversation in social media, by finding content from a list of trustworthy sources of experts/researchers who engage on social media (mainly on Twitter). This project involved working with R on remote servers and Shiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Núcleo Jornalismo&lt;/a&gt;: data analysis and, eventually, write stories published at &lt;em&gt;Núcleo Jornalismo&lt;/em&gt;. Recently, &lt;em&gt;Núcleo&lt;/em&gt; has focused on the impacts of social media on society, but I also produced stories about other topics. My contributions were on stories on &lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/nucleo_politica/&#34;&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;/en/blog/nucleo_redes/&#34;&gt;social media&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/en/software/&#34;&gt;R Packages&lt;/a&gt;: three packages to extract data from APIs developed by Volt Data Lab: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sergiospagnuolo/pollingBR/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pollingBR&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which gets data about electoral polls compiled by news website Poder360;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/voltdatalab/crossfire&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;crossfire&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which gets data about gun shootings in Rio de Janeiro and Recife&amp;rsquo;s metropolitan areas, collected by the Fogo Cruzado initiative; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/voltdatalab/newsatlasbr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;newsatlasbr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which extracts data from the Brazilian News Atlas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.voltdata.info/conteudo/2019/estatsticas-de-podcasts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Data and statics on podcasts in Brazil, 2019 (in Portuguese)&lt;/a&gt;: report produced by Sérgio Spagnuolo and I, in which we collected and analyzed data on Brazilian and International podcasts hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pocketcasts.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pocket Casts&lt;/a&gt;. Data were collected in July and August 2019 and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sergiospagnuolo/pesquisa-podcasts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code can be found on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tierraderesistentes.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Terra de Resistentes&lt;/a&gt;: a collaborative project which investigates threats to environmental leaders and their communities in seven countries in Latin America. I contributed with data analysis and visualization on &lt;a href=&#34;https://tierraderesistentes.com/en/index.php/2020/03/06/el-cercado-indigena/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;threats to indigenous communities in Rondônia&lt;/a&gt;. This story involved data analysis from indigenous lands, deforestation, illegal roads, hydrography, mining, and rural lands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How does the pandemic affects elections?</title>
      <link>/en/blog/pandemia_eleicoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/pandemia_eleicoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://noticias.uol.com.br/colunas/observatorio-das-eleicoes/2020/10/15/como-a-pandemia-afeta-as-eleicoes.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;In this article&lt;/a&gt; (in Portuguese), I evaluate the scientific evidence about the impact of Covid-19 on worldwide elections, to think how might they apply to the Brazilian 2020 local elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article was published on the &amp;ldquo;Electoral Observatory&amp;rdquo; section of &lt;em&gt;UOL&lt;/em&gt;, a Brazilian news website, on October, 15th, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The advantages of reelection</title>
      <link>/en/blog/vantagens_reeleicao/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/vantagens_reeleicao/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www1.folha.uol.com.br/opiniao/2020/09/as-vantagens-da-reeleicao.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Article published at &lt;em&gt;Folha de S. Paulo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, on 24 sep. 2020. I contest former president Fernando Henrique Cardoso&amp;rsquo;s objection to reelection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is considerable evidence in the literature that reelection might not imply electoral or financial advantages, as well as it can induce the elected behavior and be an instrument of accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I suggest caution on reform proposals, but also institutional creativity in case legislators decide to pursue this theme.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electoral Geography</title>
      <link>/en/blog/geografia_eleicoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/geografia_eleicoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In August 2020, I participated in a &amp;ldquo;live&amp;rdquo; about electoral geography, in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLnOtuNzPX7Jf9rpfvzIHa6ZlQLnnXKpz2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;We R Live&lt;/a&gt; series (about spatial analysis with R) from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCLAeX4dyujMoy4xqHvxSDpQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Geocast&lt;/a&gt; channel. In my presentation, I talked about how political science uses geography (theoretically and methodologically) to study elections, especially in Brazil. I also discussed the strengths and weaknesses of using R in these analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To those interested in learning more about using R for spatial analysis, Geocast&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;We R Live&amp;rdquo; series is an excellent starting point. Over the last few years, there was a shortage of materials on how to use R for this goal, especially in Portuguese. Since the development of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://r-spatial.github.io/sf/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, this has been changing and this series is an excellent example of this trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KN4kkvKkb_w&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>São Paulo: subnational alignment and challenges from Covid-19 in the country&#39;s largest city</title>
      <link>/en/blog/sp_covid19/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/sp_covid19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nepolufjf.wordpress.com/2020/04/07/sao-paulo-alinhamento-subnacional-e-os-desafios-do-combate-a-covid-19-na-maior-cidade-do-pais/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How did the city of São Paulo respond to the first weeks&amp;rsquo; challenges of the new coronavirus pandemic?&lt;/a&gt;.
In this blog post, I described the first measures taken by mayor Bruno Covas (PSDB) and his relationship with governor João Doria (PSDB). I also discussed the main health, social care, and urban transportation policies during this period. To conclude, I pointed out some of the challenges the city was poised to face: how to maintain isolation policies, reach vulnerable populations, increase testing and hospital capacities, and planning the economy reopening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nepolufjf.wordpress.com/2020/04/07/sao-paulo-alinhamento-subnacional-e-os-desafios-do-combate-a-covid-19-na-maior-cidade-do-pais/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This post was published on April 7th, 2020, in Portuguese (original title &amp;ldquo;São Paulo: alinhamento subnacional e os desafios do combate à Covid-19 na maior cidade do país&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt; in the blog series &lt;a href=&#34;https://nepolufjf.wordpress.com/os-governos-municipais-frente-ao-coronavirus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Municipal governments facing the coronavirus&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; from the Study Group on Local Politics (NEPOL), Federal University of Juiz de Fora.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unlike other world leaders, Bolsonaro&#39;s evaluation does not change during the pandemic</title>
      <link>/en/blog/bolsonaro_aprovacao/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/bolsonaro_aprovacao/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How did Jair Bolsonaro&amp;rsquo;s evaluation was compared to other world leaders in the first weeks of the new coronavirus pandemic? &lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleo.jor.br/pesquisas/2020-04-01-popularidade-bolsonaro-lideres-coronavirus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;By comparing surveys about the Brazilian president&amp;rsquo;s approval rating with others from seven world leaders&lt;/a&gt;, I found that, unlike the others, Bolsonaro was the only one who did not get a bump on his approval ratings in the period. I analyzed the result from the perspective of the &lt;em&gt;rally-round-the-flag effect&lt;/em&gt; which can explain political leaders&amp;rsquo; sudden increase in approval during hard times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis published in portuguese on &lt;em&gt;Núcleo Jornalismo&lt;/em&gt;, on April 1st, 2020. Original title: &lt;em&gt;Na contramão de outros líderes, avaliação de Bolsonaro fica estagnada durante pandemia&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1v5-qq_4eLAi-Putcgc7pTkdcCUR5q97wuWZr0JQqwXE/edit#gid=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/lgelape/7022068fe55e18c7a100cfceb01a70d9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; are available on the hyperlinks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News stories on G1</title>
      <link>/en/blog/materias_g1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/materias_g1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./g1.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From July to November 2018, I worked on the news website &lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;G1&lt;/a&gt;, when I wrote stories on politics, especially about the Brazilian general elections. In this post, I gather the links for all the stories I produced (or co-produced). Most of them were published in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Election in Numbers&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em&gt;Eleição em Números&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; section, and were about many topics, including campaign and party finance, female candidates quotas, reelection, polls, candidate and electorate profile and electoral results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/noticia/2018/07/29/em-23-das-cidades-do-pais-partidos-nao-declaram-despesas-de-2017.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;In 2/3 of the cities, parties have not declared the 2017 expenses&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Em 2/3 das cidades do país, partidos não declaram despesas de 2017. 29 jul. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/11/07/resultados-da-votacao-por-urna-mostram-dobradinhas-na-maioria-dos-estados-no-2o-turno.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Polling place results show &amp;ldquo;straight ballot&amp;rdquo; votes in most runoff elections&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Resultados da votações por urna mostram dobradinha na maioria dos estados no 2º turno. 07 nov. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/09/16/quase-3-em-cada-4-deputados-estaduais-e-federais-da-ultima-legislatura-buscam-novo-mandato.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Almost 3 in 4 state and federal deputies are running for reelection&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Quase 3 em cada 4 deputados estaduais e federais da última legislatura buscam novo mandato. 16 sep. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/24/mesmo-com-lei-proporcao-de-mulheres-nao-aumenta-nas-eleicoes-e-justica-precisa-notificar-coligacoes-para-que-cumpram-cota.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Even with new law, proportion of women does not increase in Election and the Court needs to notify parties to fulfill gender quotas.&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Mesmo com lei, proporção de mulheres não aumenta nas eleições e Justiça precisa notificar coligações para que cumpram cota. 24 aug. 2018 (with Clara Velasco, Gabriela Sarmento and Lucas Vidigal)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/08/numero-de-policiais-e-militares-no-legislativo-e-quatro-vezes-maior-do-que-o-de-2014.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Number of police and military officers elected for legislative position is four times larger than in 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Número de policiais e militares no Legislativo é quatro vezes maior do que o de 2014. 08 oct. 2018. (with Gabriela Caesar and Ana Carolina Moreno)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/31/mais-de-300-cidades-do-pais-tem-mais-eleitores-que-habitantes.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Over 300 cities in the country have more registered voters than inhabitants&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Mais de 300 cidades do país têm mais eleitores que habitantes. 31 aug. 2018. (with Clara Velasco)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/11/10/gastos-de-campanha-no-1o-turno-das-eleicoes-caem-pela-metade-em-comparacao-a-2014.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Campaing expenses on the first round of elections dropped from half the amount of 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Gastos de campanha no 1º turno das eleições caem pela metade em comparação a 2014. 10 nov. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/11/02/cidades-de-mg-quase-repetem-resultado-da-eleicao-para-presidente-em-ambos-os-turnos.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cities from MG almost repeat the national share of votes in both rounds of the 2018 elections&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Cidades de MG quase repetem resultado da eleição para presidente em ambos os turnos. 02 nov. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/29/haddad-vira-em-1-estado-e-em-116-cidades-bolsonaro-fatura-25-municipios-vencidos-pelo-pt-no-1o-turno.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Haddad registers comebacks in 1 state and 117 cities; Bolsonaro wins in 25 cities where the PT had a majority of votes in the first round&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Haddad vira em 1 estado e 117 cidades; Bolsonaro fatura 25 municípios vencidos pelo PT no 1º turno. 29 oct. 2018. (with Clara Velasco)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/29/20-governadores-tentaram-reeleicao-em-2018-10-conseguiram.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;20 governors attempted reelection in 2018. Only 10 were successful&lt;/a&gt;. Original: 20 governadores tentaram a reeleição em 2018; 10 conseguiram. 29 oct. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/19/metade-dos-deputados-estaduais-e-distritais-eleitos-em-2014-conquista-novo-mandato-em-2018.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Half the state and federal deputies elected in 2014 were reelected in 2018&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Metade dos deputados estaduais e distritais eleitos em 2014 conquista novo mandato em 2018. 19 oct. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/11/diferenca-entre-candidatos-na-1a-pesquisa-de-2o-turno-e-a-maior-desde-2002-segundo-datafolha.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Difference between candidates in the first poll from the second round is the largest since 2002, according to  Datafolha&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Diferença entre candidatos na 1ª pesquisa de segundo turno é a maior desde 2002, segundo Datafolha. 11 oct. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/11/cai-o-numero-de-deputados-eleitos-que-usam-titulo-religioso-no-nome-de-urna-ou-se-declaram-como-membro-de-ordem-religiosa.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The number of elected deputies with a religious title have fallen in the 2018 elections&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Cai o número de deputados eleitos que usam título religioso no nome de urna ou se declaram como membro de ordem religiosa. 11 oct. 2018. (with Thiago Lavado)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/09/apenas-4-dos-candidatos-eleitos-para-cargos-de-senador-e-deputado-estadual-e-federal-sao-pretos.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Only 4% of the elected candidates for Legislative seats in 2018 are black&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Apenas 4% dos candidatos eleitos para cargo de senador e deputado estadual e federal são pretos. 09 oct. 2018. (with Carolina Dantas)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/08/menos-da-metade-dos-deputados-federais-eleitos-em-2014-consegue-se-reeleger-nestas-eleicoes.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Less than half of the federal deputies elected in 2014 were reelected in 2018&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Menos da metade dos deputados federais eleitos em 2014 consegue se reeleger nestas eleições. 08 oct. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/10/02/percentual-de-mulheres-que-nao-escolheram-um-presidenciavel-a-10-dias-das-eleicoes-e-o-maior-desde-1998-segundo-datafolha.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Percentage of women who have not chosen a presidential candidate 10 days to the election is the highest since 1998, according to Datafolha&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Percentual de mulheres que não escolheram um presidenciável a 10 dias das eleições é o maior desde 1998, segundo Datafolha. 02 oct. 2018. (with Rafael Miotto)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/09/30/primeira-parcial-indica-queda-de-36-nos-gastos-de-campanha-em-2018.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;First results points to a 36% decrease in campaign expenses in 2018&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Primeira parcial indica queda de 36% nos gastos de campanha em 2018. 30 sep. 2018. (with Cauê Muraro and Leandro Oliveira)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/09/11/saude-e-violencia-sao-os-principais-problemas-para-os-eleitores-brasileiros-segundo-datafolha.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Health and violence are the two main problems to brazilian voters, according to Datafolha poll&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Saúde e violência são os principais problemas para os eleitores brasileiros, segundo Datafolha. 11 sep. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/27/pesquisas-ibope-rj-e-am-tem-mais-eleitores-que-se-dizem-insatisfeitos-ou-muito-insatisfeitos-com-a-vida-atual.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ibope polls: RJ and AM have the most voters who says they are unsatisfied or very unsatisfied with their current life&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Pesquisas Ibope: RJ e AM têm mais eleitores que se dizem &amp;lsquo;insatisfeitos&amp;rsquo; ou &amp;lsquo;muito insatisfeitos&amp;rsquo; com a vida atual. 27 aug. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/27/pesquisas-ibope-lula-atinge-pelo-menos-50-em-todos-os-estados-do-nordeste-e-bolsonaro-e-mais-forte-em-rr-ac-e-df.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ibope polls: Lula reaches at least 50% in all Northeastern states and Bolsonaro is the strongest in RR, AC and DF&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Pesquisas Ibope: Lula atinge pelo menos 50% em todos os estados do Nordeste e Bolsonaro é mais forte em RR, AC e DF. 27 aug. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/26/saude-e-o-problema-mais-citado-pelos-eleitores-nos-estados-do-pais-apontam-pesquisas-ibope.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Health is the problem most cited by voters over the country, according to Ibope polls&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Saúde é o problema mais citado pelos eleitores nos estados do país, apontam pesquisas Ibope. 26 aug. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/20/mais-de-500-candidatos-usam-titulos-religiosos-no-nome-de-urna.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Over 500 candidates use religious titles in their polling registries&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Mais de 500 candidatos usam títulos religiosos no nome de urna. 20 aug. 2018. (with Rafaela Putini)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/17/aumentam-pedidos-de-candidaturas-de-policiais-e-militares-ativos-e-inativos.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Higher numbers of candidate registries from current and retired military were found in 2018&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Aumentam pedidos de candidaturas de militares ativos e inativos. 17 aug. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://g1.globo.com/politica/eleicoes/2018/eleicao-em-numeros/noticia/2018/08/15/proporcao-de-eleitores-com-voto-facultativo-nas-eleicoes-e-a-mais-baixa-das-ultimas-eleicoes.ghtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Proportion of voters that are not required to vote is the lowest in the last election&lt;/a&gt;. Original: Proporção de eleitores com voto facultativo é a mais baixa das últimas eleições. 15 aug. 2018. (com Clara Velasco e Leandro Oliveira)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Territorial Representation and Marielle Franco</title>
      <link>/en/blog/marielle_franco/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/marielle_franco/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In March 2018, after a news website published a short note Marielle Franco&amp;rsquo;s number of votes at the Maré neighborhood, I published an analysis on &lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt; called &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@lgelape/representa%C3%A7%C3%A3o-territorial-e-marielle-franco-b1884061bf1c&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Territorial Representation and Marielle Franco&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (in Portuguese), which showed how her votes were distributed across the city of Rio de Janeiro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the text, I discuss some precautions and data issues for spatial analysis of Brazilian elections, and I also present some ideas on &amp;ldquo;territorial representation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code used in the analysis is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lgelape/texto_mariellefranco&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;in a repo on my GitHub profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./vereadores_PSOL.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class speakers, Graduation Class in Law, UFMG, 2nd semester of 2015</title>
      <link>/en/blog/direito_ufmg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/blog/direito_ufmg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In January, 2015, with Amanda Cristina Viana, I was one of the class speakers of the 2014 2nd semester graduation class. The UFMG Law School Journal (&lt;em&gt;Revista da Faculdade de Direito da UFMG&lt;/em&gt;) was kind to publish in its &lt;a href=&#34;https://revista.direito.ufmg.br/index.php/revista/article/view/1691&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;issue 66 &lt;em&gt;Historical Memory&lt;/em&gt; section&lt;/a&gt; (in Portuguese).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
